<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rudiments of militarie discipline Conteining short instructions for the most necessary postures with pike and musquet, and motions for exercising a companie.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11175</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21441</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101399</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837214</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837214</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1529</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11175)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1529)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1392:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rudiments of militarie discipline Conteining short instructions for the most necessary postures with pike and musquet, and motions for exercising a companie.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for James Bryson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Militarie instructions.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Drill and minor tactics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Military art and science --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1529:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1529:1"/>
            <p>THE RUDIMENTS OF MILITARIE <hi>DISCIPLINE:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conteining ſhort inſtructions for the <hi>moſt neceſſary poſtures with Pike</hi> and Muſquet, and motions for exerciſing a companie.</p>
            <figure>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nehem.</hi> 4.19.20. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jude,</hi> verſ. 3.</p>
            </figure>
            <p>EDINBURGH, Printed for <hi>James Bryſon,</hi> 1638.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1529:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1529:2"/>
            <div n="musket" type="posture">
               <head>
                  <hi>POSTURES</hi> OF THE <hi>MUSQUET.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake up your Muſquet, and your Reſt, Recover your Muſquet, and joine it to your reſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Take out your match, blow your match.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Cock your match, try your match, guarde your Pan.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Advance three ſteps, with blowing your match, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, Open your Pan, and give fire.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Joine your Muſquet to your reſt againe.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Recover your match, blow your Pan and prime it, Put of your louſe powlder.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Caſt about your Muſquet and your reſt.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Charge with poulder, chape the Muſquet a little a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the earth.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Charge with Bullet, Chape it a little againſt the earth.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb facs="tcp:1529:3"/>10. Recover your Muſquet, and Joine it againe to your reſt. Cocke your match, &amp;c. Againe as before, making readie for ſervice. When yee have done with ſervice, weigh your Muſquet with your right hand, Lay it on your left ſhoulder, holding the butt with your left hand, and the reſt alſo.</p>
               <p>Nota.</p>
               <p>¶ It is to bee remembered that the mouth of the Musket be alwayes upward in exerciſe, for being low, if a ſparke of fire ſhould goe in the Pan, it might ſhoote your neighbour: Alſo when your Musket is ſhouldered in marching, hold the mouth of your Muſquet high, for the reaſon foreſaid, and for diſturbing your follower.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="pike" type="posture">
               <head>Poſtures of the <hi>Pike.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <item>TAke up your Pike.</item>
                  <item>Overend, or order your pike.</item>
                  <item>Shoulder your pike.</item>
                  <item>Mount your pike.</item>
                  <item>Charge to the front.</item>
                  <item>Charge to the right hand.</item>
                  <item>Charge to the left hand.</item>
                  <item>Right about to the reer.</item>
                  <item>Left about to the reer.</item>
                  <item>March, and charge.</item>
                  <item>Lay down your pike.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Nota.</p>
               <p>¶ All your exerciſes both of Musket and Pike would be at open order, that is, ſix foot diſtant between every man in the Ranke, and between each Ranke, and that for doubling
<pb facs="tcp:1529:3"/>
of Rankes. Alſo when yee come either to be expert; or comes u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſervice, the ordinare distance is three foot, which is called order: And ſometime may come to clo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e order; when ſidemen cloſe ſhoulder to ſhoulder, and the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt of the Rankes cloſe up to the ſword point, ſpecially Pickemen againſt horſe.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Motiones.</head>
            <p>MOtiones are either in keeping ground, or changeing ground, and are either of the whole or of a part: Keeping ground, when everie one move in his proper place, as in faceing: Changeing ground, as in Countermarch and wheeling: The motion of a part is as in doubleing, cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and opening files and rankes, where ſome move and ſome ſtand ſtill, And firſt of keeping ground and faceing being ſtanding in order.</p>
            <div n="facing" type="motion">
               <head>Of Faceing.</head>
               <p>WHen yee are commanded <hi>To face to the right hand,</hi> ſtand firme with the left legge, and fall backe with the right legge, and ſo yee are faced to the right hand, <hi>As yee were,</hi> bring forward againe that ſame right legge, and place it where it ſtood firſt.</p>
               <p>When yee are commanded to <hi>Face to the left hand,</hi> bring forward the right leg, and ſo your face will be to the left hand, <hi>As you were,</hi> bring your right leg to the former ſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1529:4"/>When you are commanded to <hi>face to the right and left hand by diviſion,</hi> the halfe of the files to the right hand faceth to the right, as is before ſet downe, and the halfe of the files to the left hand, as is before ſet downe: <hi>As you were.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When you are commanded to <hi>face to the reere by the right hand,</hi> hold firme your left legge, turning upon your left heele: Draw back your right legge, till your face bee to the reer. <hi>As you were.</hi> Turn upon your left heele, and bring about your right legge.</p>
               <p>When you are commanded to <hi>face to the reere by the left hand,</hi> turne on your left heele, and bring forward your right legge, till your face bee to the reere: <hi>As you were;</hi> Turne on your heele, and bring back your right legge.</p>
               <p>The motion of a part is doubling ranks and files, &amp;c. Doubling of rankes ſerve to enlarge and ſtrengthen the length of the battell, doubling of files to ſtrengthen the deepe of the battell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="doubling" type="motion">
               <head>Of doubleing of Rankes.</head>
               <p>VVHen you are commanded to <hi>double your ranks to the right hand,</hi> the ſecond rank doubleth to the firſt, the fourth to the third, the ſext to the fift, and ſo foorth every one of theſe ſtepping up to the right ſide of his leader, with three ſteppes beginning with the left legge, ſtepping up on the right hand, with the right legge, and then
<pb facs="tcp:1529:4"/>
bringing up the left legge: <hi>As you were,</hi> returning by the left hand; Alſo with three ſteppes to your owne place.</p>
               <p>When you are commanded to <hi>double your rankes to the left hand,</hi> ſtep foreward as to the right: <hi>As you were,</hi> but returne by the right hand.</p>
               <p>Next, ranks are doubled by bringers up, when men are more perfectly trained; that is, being ten rankes: the left rank doubleth by the right or left hand to the firſt rank, the ninth to the ſecond, the eight to the third, &amp;c. Or ranks are doubled by middle-men, when the laſt five rankes of ten double up to the firſt five through the voide that is betweene the files: And being commanded againe <hi>As you were,</hi> returne againe to their owne place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="doubling" type="motion">
               <head>Of doubling files, <hi>or ſtrings.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHen you are commanded to <hi>double your files to the right hand,</hi> the right hand file ſtandeth ſtill, and the next file unto it, each man ſteppeth in behinde his ſide-man: firſt, turning about the face to the right hand, ſetting foreward the right legge ſteppes foreward, with their left legge behinde their ſide-men on the right hand, bringeth up their legge, placing their bodie in a right line behinde their leader, <hi>As you were,</hi> They muſt turne about their face, moving firſt their left legge, and thus with three ſteps recover their ſtation.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1529:5"/>When yee are commanded to <hi>double your files to the left hand,</hi> the files that formerly moved, ſtand, and the other come in behinde them, turning your face about, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning your motion with their left legge with three ſteppes, and being commanded, <hi>As you were,</hi> returnes by the right legge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="counter-march" type="motion">
               <head>Of Counter-march.</head>
               <p>VVHen yee are commanded <hi>Files to the right hand counter march,</hi> then all the file-leaders together at one inſtant ſteppe forward with the right legge, and bringing about their left legge, turne their bodie to the right hand, and ſo marche down thorow the files, till they come to the place of the bringers up or laſt ranke, all that follow the file-leader, muſt not offer to turn, before they have come up to the place of the file lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and every follower muſt remarke and keep that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance with his leader which hee had before they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to counter-march: <hi>As you were:</hi> ſteppe forward with the right legge, and caſt about the left legge to the right hand, and ſo march back to your place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Files Counter-march to the left hand,</hi> ſteppe forward with the left legge, bringing about the right legge, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning your body to the left hand, and march down as the former. <hi>As you were,</hi> ſtep forward with your left legge, caſt about the right legge to the left hand, and ſo
<pb facs="tcp:1529:5"/>
march back to your place: Other kindes of counter-march is not fitte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="closing and opening" type="motion">
               <head>Cloſeing, and opening <hi>of Rankes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHen yee are commanded <hi>to cloſe your rankes;</hi> the firſt ranke ſtandeth ſtill: the ſecond cometh up, and cloſeth to the diſtance commanded, either three foote, or cloſe order: the reſt of the ranks move up, and cloſe to the ſame diſtance.</p>
               <p>When yee are commanded to <hi>open your rankes,</hi> the firſt ranke ſtandeth ſtill, the reſt fall backe towards the reere: the ſecond taketh its diſtance, and ſtandeth ſtill, ſo the third till all have got their places.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="closing and opening" type="motion">
               <head>Cloſeing, and opening <hi>of Files.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHen yee are commanded to <hi>cloſe your files to the right hand,</hi> the right hand file ſtandeth, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond file to it faceth about to it, and ſteppeth forward, till it have taken the diſtance commanded, ſo doth the reſt in order, each after other.</p>
               <p>If yee be commanded to <hi>cloſe your files to the left hand,</hi> the left hand file ſtandeth ſtill, and the reſt cloſe to it, as they did to the right hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1529:6"/>If yee be commanded to <hi>cloſe your files to the middle,</hi> if yee be ten or ſix in ranke, the two middle files take their diſtance, the reſt face to them, and the neareſt to them take firſt their diſtance, and ſo the reſt in order: But this is little needfull; the other two may ſerve.</p>
               <p>When yee are commanded to <hi>open your files to the right hand,</hi> the left hand file ſtandeth ſtill, the ſecond to it openeth, and all the reſt in order, till yee come to the right hand.</p>
               <p>When yee are commanded to <hi>open your files to the left hand,</hi> the right hand file ſtandeth ſtill, and openeth as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly to the left hand.</p>
               <p>When yee are commanded to <hi>open files to both the hands,</hi> the two middle files open to their juſt diſtances, ſo preſſe on the reſt neereſt to them, till all have opened to the diſtance commanded, and open by ſtepping ſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, preſſing with their ſhoulder their ſideman.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="wheeling" type="motion">
               <head>Of wheeling, or the <hi>great turne.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHen ye are commanded <hi>the great turne to the right hand,</hi> yee muſt firſt cloſe your files to that hand, whereto yee are to turne, even to cloſſe order, and cloſe up your rankes to the ſame order: Then the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner-file-leader on the right hand ſtandeth ſtill in his place, as the fixed foote of a Compaſſe, moving with the left legge about, turning on the right foot fixed, his ſideman moveth more, and ſo alwayes the more, the further they
<pb facs="tcp:1529:6"/>
are removed from him, every follower keeping his lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and in every ranke their ſideman, The further they are from the right ſide, they will make the larger turne, untill the front be where the right flanke was: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing commanded <hi>the great turne to the reere by the right hand,</hi> haveing now your front where your right flank was, may keepe the ſame order as at firſt, till your faces be at the reere. When yee would reduce them: <hi>As they were,</hi> even to the place where they were firſt, yee muſt wheele them juſt about to the ſaid firſt place: Then opening their files and rankes, they are juſt as they were: yee may do juſt ſo when yee are commanded to make the great turne to the left hand, onlie they do at the left hand, as the other did at the right hand before; but this motion is ſeldome uſed, and would be performed when your men are perfite in all their other motions.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
